Finding Aid for Thomas Harrison Reed Papers
Bentley Historical Library
Thomas Harrison Reed Papers
1902-1971
Bentley Historical Library
Reed, Thomas Harrison, 1881-
85406 Aa 2
8 linear feet
Consultant in municipal government, professor of political science at the University of California and the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other papers concerning his work with the National Municipal League, as municipal consultant, and as director of studies of the Republican Program Committee.
The collection was donated by Mrs. Doris D. Reed (donor no. 5326 ) in 1974.
The collection is open for research.
Reed's career in municipal government began in 1909 and extended well into the 1960s. During this period Dr. Reed held many positions, including Professor of Municipal Government at the University of California, Berkeley, Executive Secretary to the Governor of California, City Manager of San Jose, California, Consultant for the National Municipal League, Director of the National Municipal League's Consultant Services, and privately employed municipal consultant. In his role as municipal consultant, Reed studied the administration and organization of many American cities, including Atlanta, Augusta, Charleston, S.C., Pittsburgh, Cincinnati, Cleveland, Baton Rouge, Shreveport, Norfolk, Richmond, and Hartford, Connecticut.
Dr. Reed was an active member of the American Political Science Association and he maintained a strong interest in Belgium during much of his life. He published a study of Belgian government in 1924, assisted in the translation of Leopold of the Belgians (1929), participated in the activities of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, and was an officer in the Order of Leopold.
Thomas Harrison Reed was born in Boston in 1881. He was educated at Harvard University where he received his AB in 1901 and his LL.B. in 1904. He did post-graduate work at Columbia University in 1908 and 1909 and received an LL. D. from the University of Brussels in 1930. Dr. Reed was a Professor of Political Science at The University of Michigan from 1922 until 1936 when he resigned to devote his full attention to his duties as Director of Consultant Services for the National Municipal League, a position which he held since 1933. Dr. Reed served as Director of Studies for the Republican Program Committee during 1938 and 1939 and thereafter he was a privately employed municipal consultant. Throughout his career, Reed maintained a close association with the National Municipal League and was active in the League's affairs. Reed also held positions on many councils and commissions involved with the study of government in many communities. During his lifetime, Reed was often in contact with such luminaries of the American intellectual establishment as Charles A. Beard, A. Lawrence Lowell, and Charles E. Merriam. Dr. Reed was an accomplished public speaker and a prolific author of books and articles on a variety of topics relating to government. He died in Wethersfield, Connecticut in 1971.
The Thomas Harrison Reed Collection is the papers of a man who was an active and important figure in the field of municipal government during much of the first half of this century. The Reed papers consist of eight feet of manuscript material, including correspondence, memos, newspaper clippings, and printed material. Over half of the collection deals primarily with Reed's work as a municipal consultant. The collection also contains a substantial amount of material which pertains to Reed's activities in connection with the American Political Science Association as well as material which relates to his academic career and correspondence with Michigan citizens and legislators and Michigan's Congressional representatives. In addition, the collection includes material on Belgium, Reed's work as city manager of San Jose, and his work with the Republican Program Committee.
The Thomas Harrison Reed Collection provides useful material for research on the history of the activities of the National Municipal League and on trends and issues in municipal government during the first half of the twentieth century in the United States. The collection is also useful to anyone interested in the issues which were involved in the revision of city charters in many American cities during the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s. The collection contains, in particular, substantial material on reform in Atlanta during the 1930s.
Although this collection contains material on Reed's association with The University of Michigan and some material which deals with government in Michigan, it would be of little use for research on any aspect of Michigan history. During his twelve-year residence in Michigan, Reed did little work which related specifically to municipal government in this state. He did publish Oakland County: a survey of county and township administration and finance in 1932, but the collection contains nothing of substance relating to this work. With this exception, and aside from some correspondence and a few speeches to such groups as the League of Women Voters, there is no material in this collection which would be of more than passing interest to one engaged in historical research relating to Michigan.
China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949.; Japanese Americans.; Municipal government.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1929-1933.; Bands.; Photographs.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; National Municipal League.; Reed, Thomas Harrison, 1881-; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854-); University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; Reed, Thomas Harrison, 1881-; Allin, Cephas Daniel, 1875-1927.; Atwood, Albert William, 1879-1975.; Barrows, David P., 1873-1954.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.; Brownlow, Louis, 1879-; Crane, Robert Treat, 1880-; Fairlie, John A. (John Archibald), 1872-1947.; Foster, William Trufant, 1879-1950.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Lowell, A. Lawrence (Abbott Lawrence), 1856-1943.; Malone, Dudley Field, 1882-1950.; Merriam, Charles Edward, 1874-1953.; Munro, William Bennett, 1875-1957.; Ogg, Frederic Austin, 1878-1951.; Putnam, George Haven, 1844-1930.; Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942.; Shattuck, Henry Lee, 1879-1971.; Shurtleff, Flavel, 1879-1978.; Smith, Harold Dewey, 1898-1947.; Teggart, Frederick John, 1870-1946.; Upson, Lent Dayton, 1886-1949.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Vanderbilt, Arthur T., 1888-1957.; White, Leonard Dupee, 1891-1958.
- Biographical and Personal
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1902, 1907-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1913-1947, 48 folders (Box 1)
  - 1948-1971, 28 folders (Box 2)
  - Re translation of Leopold II, 1927-1929 (Box 2)
  - Re translation of Leopold I, 1929-1931 (Box 2)
  - With World Book Company
    - 1913, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
    - 1923-1924 (Box 2)
    - 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926-1928 (Box 2)
    - 1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930-1932 (Box 2)
- Consultation files
  - Michigan County Home Rule Amendment, 1929; 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Oakland County 1932 Bloomfield Hills, 1932 Michigan, 1933, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - Yonkers, N.Y., 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Cortlandt, Greenburgh, Harrison, Mt. Pleasant, Mt. Vernon (N.Y. State), 1934 (Box 2)
  - Lehigh Co., Pa., 1934 (Box 2)
  - Kearny, N.J., 1934 (Box 2)
  - North Bergen, N.J., 1934 (Box 2)
  - Nassau County, N.Y. (Box 3)
    - Papers, 1934-1935; 1941 (Box 3)
    - The Government of Nassau County Special Reports, 1934 (Box 3)
      (3 volumes in one)
  - Coral Gables, Fla., 1934; 1941; 1945 (Box 3)
  - Asbury Park, N.J., 1935 (Box 3)
  - Teaneck, N.J., 1935 (Box 3)
  - Jersey City, N.J., 1935 (Box 3)
  - Borough of Dumont, N.J., 1935 (Box 3)
  - Woodbridge Twp., N.J., 1936 (Box 3)
  - St. Petersburg, Fla.
    - Report: Financial and Administrative Survey of the City of St. Petersburg, Fla., 1936; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - Report: Financial and Administrative Survey of the City of St. Petersburg, Fla.: Special Report on Municipal Utilities 1936 (Box 3)
  - Inverness, Fla., 1936 (Box 3)
  - Brookline, Mass., 1937 (Box 3)
  - Atlanta, Ga.
    - Papers, 1937-1938; 1940 (Box 3)
    - Report: The Governments of Atlanta and Fulton County Georgia, 1938; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - Papers, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Savannah, Ga., 1937; 1947 (Box 3)
  - Bergenfield, N.J., 1938 (Box 3)
  - Richmond, Va.
    - Papers, 1939-1953; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Papers, 1960-1964 (Box 3)
    - Published material, 1947; 1950; 1961; 4 volumes (Box 4)
    - Annexation trial proceedings, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1947-1963 (Box 4)
  - Rome, N.Y., 1942 (Box 4)
  - Roanoke, Va.
    - Papers, 1942; 1946-1948 (Box 4)
    - Annexation trial proceedings, 1948; 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Wallingford, Conn., 1943 (Box 4)
  - Petersburg, Va., 1943-1944; 1946-1948 (Box 4)
  - Cincinnati, Ohio
    - Papers, 1943-1944 (Box 4)
    - Papers, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Papers, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Litchfield, Conn., 1944 (Box 4)
  - Simsbury, Conn., 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Cleveland, Ohio, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Cleveland, Ohio Hospital, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
  - Augusta, Ga.
    - Papers, 1944-1948; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1943-1947 (Box 4)
  - Bloomfield, Conn., 1945 (Box 5)
  - Farmington, Conn., 1945 (Box 5)
  - Hartford, Conn., 1946 (Box 5)
  - Norwich, Conn., 1946 (Box 5)
  - Southington, Conn., 1946-1947 (Box 5)
  - Tarrytown, N.Y.
    - Papers, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
  - Baton Rouge, La.
    - Papers, 1946-1947; 1949-1950; 1956; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
  - Wethersfield, Conn., 1947 (Box 5)
  - Ossining, Westchester Co., N.Y., 1947 (Box 5)
  - Minneapolis, Minn., 1947; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Hoboken, N.J., 1947-1948; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Front Royal, Va., 1948 (Box 5)
  - Hopewell, Va., 1948 (Box 5)
  - Danville, Va.
    - Papers, 1948-1950 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1948-1951 (Box 5)
  - Norfolk, Va.
    - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
  - Shreveport, La., 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - Durham, N.C., 1949-1950 (Box 6)
  - Falls Church, Va., 1949-1950; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - New Britain, Conn., 1949-1950 (Box 6)
  - Nashville, Tenn., 1951 (Box 6)
  - Niagara Falls, N.Y., 1953-1954; 1958; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Bayonne, N.J.
    - Papers, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Report The High Cost of Government in Bayonne, 1954; 1 volume (Box 6)
  - Manchester, Conn, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Oregon (Legislative Interim Committee on Local Government), 1956 (Box 6)
  - Charleston, S.C., 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - Warwick, R.I., 1957 (Box 6)
  - Barrington, R.I., 1958 (Box 6)
  - Columbus, Ohio
    - Papers, 1958-1959; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - Norwalk, Conn., 1959; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Cedar Rapids, Iowa, 1959; 1961 (Box 6)
  - Cranston, R.I.
    - Papers, 1960-1961 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
- Organizational files
  - Commission to Study Municipal Consolidation, Pa., 1928 (Box 6)
  - Citizen's Metropolitan Committee of 1000 St. Louis, Mo.
    - Papers, 1929-1931; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1929-1931 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Tax Survey Committee, 1933; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Republican Party Program Committee
    - Reports, 1939; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Papers, 1938-1940; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Reports and work plans, 1938-1939; 5 volumes (Box 7)
  - No Third Term Association, 1940 (Box 7)
  - Citizenship Clearing House
    - Papers, 1947-1954; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Workshop on College Preparation for Politics, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Dartmouth College Conference on Industrial Parks, Hanover, New Hampshire, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Murray Seasongood Good Government Fund Lectures, 1959-1965; 2 folders (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Reed Festschrift material, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Book Reviews, 1924-1938 (Box 8)
  - Articles for Banking, with correspondence, 1936; 1940-1942 (Box 8)
  - Encyclopedia articles with correspondence, 1945-1967 (Box 8)
  - Speeches and Lectures, 1928-1959; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Writings and reports, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Manuscript of book, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellanea
    - Belgium related materials (Box 8)
    - Programs, invitations, agendas, 1900-1961 (Box 8)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Clippings
    - 1918, 1920s (Box 8)
    - 1930s (Box 8)
    - 1940s (Box 8)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 8)
      (Wabash, Ind. and Houston, Texas)
    - 1948 (Box 8)
      (Tampa, Fla.)
    - 1950s, 1960s (Box 8)
  - Printed material, 3 folders (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Photo of Reed speaking before unidentified group (with band in foreground) (Box 8)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Allin, Cephas Daniel, 1875-1927.
Mar. 27, 1924; Oct. 13, 1924; Oct. 11, 1924; June 30, 1926; Aug. 2, 1926; July 12, 1926; Jan. 28, 1927; Jan. 27, 1927; Jan. 24, 1927; Apr. 30, 1927; May 2, 1927
Atwood, Albert William, 1879-1975.
Undated; Aug. 20, 1928; Aug. 5, 1928; Dec. 6, 1930; Aug. 13, 1930; Jan. 2, 1931
Barrows, David Prescott, 1873-
Aug. 19, 1913; Nov. 29, 1916; July 10, 1916; July 15, 1916; Aug. 25, 1917; Oct. 10, 1917; July 6, 1921; Nov. 28, 1924; Nov. 29, 1924; 1925 throughout; June 21, 1927; July 29, 1927; Aug. 26, 1931; Jan. 27, 1932
Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.
Undated; Jan. 13, 1925; Oct. 6, 1926; Oct. 12, 1926; Dec. 18, 1926; Mar. 27, 1929; 1930?; Jan. 9, 1931; Feb. 1, 1931; Feb. 4, 1931; Feb. 6, 1931; Feb. 12, 1931; Nov. 14, 1931; Feb. 10, 1932; May 2, 1932; May 11, 1932; Jan. 8, 1932; Aug. 30, 1932; Sept. 2, 1932; Sept. 6, 1932; Sept. 29, 1932; Oct. 8, 1932; Oct. 25, 1932; July 30, 1932
Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.
1929, throughout; July 27, 1930; Nov. 10, 1959
Brownlow, Louis, b. 1879.
Oct. 31, 1924; Oct. 28, 1924; Oct. 2, 1924; Mar. 6, 1931; Mar. 4, 1931; Mar. 3, 1931; May 19, 1931; May 20, 1931; Sept. 24, 1931; Oct. 12, 1932; July 7, 1933; July 26, 1933; July 5, 1933
China
See letters, Apr. 7 and Sept. 24, 1933.
Crane, Robert Treat, b. 1880.
July 5, 1922; July 26, 1922; July 3, 1923; June 28, 1923; Aug. 2, 1924; June 6, 1925; Apr. 22, 1927
Fairlie, John A. (John Archibald), 1872-1947.
Mar. 9, 1925; Mar. 7, 1925; Feb. 2, 1925; Dec. 15, 1928; Oct. 31, 1928; Oct. 9, 1928; Oct. 10, 1928; July 19, 1931
Foster, William Trufant, 1879-1950.
Mar. 10, 1924; Mar. 11, 1925; Mar. 3, 1925; Oct. 7, 1925; May 25, 1926; Oct. 6, 1931; Dec. 21, 1931
Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.
See letter July 1, 1923, of Maximo M. Kolar to Jesse S. Reeves concerning Joseph Ralston Hayden and the Philippine Islands.
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.
Sept. 23, 1921; Aug. 28, 1926
Japanese--California
See letter Oct. 10, 1922, to Laura Mae Faville concerning the condition of Japanese citizens in California.
Lowell, A. Lawrence (Abbott Lawrence), 1856-1943.
Dec. 17, 1902; May 10, 1907; May 6, 1908; Nov. 20, 1908; Nov. 27, 1908; Jan. 15, 1909; July 1, 1924; Nov. 20, 1924; Jan. 12, 1926; Jan. 18, 1926; Jan. 7, 1927; Oct. 3, 1931; Oct. 5, 1931
Malone, Dudley Field, 1882-1950.
Jan. 18, 1928; Jan. 17, 1928
Merriam, Charles Edward, 1874-1953
Jan. 10, 1924; Dec. 3, 1924; 1925 throughout; Feb. 28, 1927; Nov. 30, 1927; Dec. 2, 1927; Dec. 5, 1927; Dec. 13, 1927; Dec. 3, 1927; Nov. 30, 1927; Dec. 21, 1927; Nov. 22, 1927; Jan. 12, 1928; Jan. 9, 1928; Jan. 7, 1928; Dec. 18, 1928; Dec. 5, 1928; Nov. 23, 1928; Nov. 21, 1928; Mar. 3, 1931; Apr. 29, 1931; Apr. 11, 1931; May 19, 1932; Mar. 5, 1932; Jan. 4, 1932; June 28, 1933
Munro, William Bennett, 1875-1957.
Undated; June 2, 1924; Oct. 2, 1925; Aug. 24, 1926; Sept. 28, 1926; Sept. 30, 1926; Oct. 26, 1926; 1927 throughout; Jan. 7, 1928; Jan. 12, 1928; Oct. 31, 1928; Nov. 28, 1928; Dec. 8, 1928; Dec. 10, 1928; Dec. 17, 1928; Jan. 9, 1929; Jan. 16, 1929; Mar. 18, 1929; Mar. 28, 1929; Oct. 23, 1951
Ogg, Frederic Austin, 1878-1951.
Aug. 11, 1921; Aug. 6, 1921; Nov. 7, 1921; Nov. 26, 1921; Apr. 6, 1925; Feb. 25, 1927; June 4, 1927; May 5, 1927; Jan. 11, 1928; Jan. 5, 1928; Apr. 9, 1931; Apr. 23, 1931; June 19, 1933; Oct. 17, 1940
Putnam, George Haven, 1844-1930.
Feb. 7, 1914
Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-
July 22, 1921; July 11, 1922; Aug. 19, 1922; Feb. 13, 1922; July 1, 1923; Feb. 16, 1924; Mar. 3, 1924; Aug. 22, 1925; May 13, 1926; Nov. 21, 1933; Jan. 29, 1936
Shattuck, Henry Lee, 1879-1971.
Sept. 23, 1924; Oct. 3, 1924; Dec. 17, 1924; Nov. 19, 1924; Nov. 14, 1924; Nov. 2, 1924; Dec. 19, 1924; June 28, 1926; Aug. 9, 1926; July 6, 1926; Feb. 21, 1927; Mar. 4, 1927; Feb. 25, 1927
Shurtleff, Flavel, 1879-
Sept. 15, 1924; Sept. 9, 1924; Dec. 23, 1924; Dec. 18, 1924; 1925 throughout; Apr. 28, 1933
Smith, Harold Dewey, 1898-1947.
Oct. 12, 1924; Oct. 11, 1927; Oct. 17, 1927; Oct. 25, 1927; Oct. 29, 1927
Teggart, Frederick John, 1870-1946.
May 8, 1924; May 16, 1924
Upson, Lent Dayton, 1886-1949.
Aug. 2, 1922; Oct. 12, 1924; Oct. 28, 1926; Oct. 23, 1926; Mar. 10, 1927; July 8, 1927
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
May 4, 1929; Oct. 31, 1932
Vanderbilt, Arthur T., 1888-1957.
Nov. 8, 1938; Jan. 23, 1939; Nov. 6, 1939; Dec. 13, 1939; Dec. 20, 1940; 1941 throughout; Oct. 13, 1942; 1943 throughout; 1944 throughout; 1945 throughout; 1947 throughout; 1948 throughout; 1949 throughout; 1950 throughout; Nov. 21, 1951; 1952 throughout; Feb. 20, 1953
White, Leonard Dupee, 1891-1958.
1925 throughout; 1926 throughout; Mar. 1929